Do you think she can do maths in her head?
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）暗算とか
できるんじゃないかなあ？
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）誰が？
Whom?
I'm talking about Nano-chan.
なのちゃんのことだよ
Nichijou 59
Since she's a robot, don't you think she might have robotic features?
ロボだから 何か
ロボっぽい機能があると思わない？
何 言ってんの？
ロボットなわけないじゃん
What are you talking about?
There's no way she's a robot.
（祐子）ええ！
だって背中にネジ付いてるんだよ
But she has a key on her back.
You think she's a robot just because of that?
えっ …って  それだけで
ロボットだと思ってるの？
There's no way that's true.
そんなわけないでしょ
No, but think about it.
いや だって考えてみてよ
ロボだよ！ ロボ
She's definitely a robot.
Isn't it amazing?
すごいじゃん！
なんつうか
Like, honestly,
すごいじゃん！
isn't it amazing?!
What is that?
何 それ 全然 理由になってないよ
There's no reasoning behind that.
というわけで―
And so, I want to investigate to see if Nano-chan is a robot.
なのちゃんが
ロボなのかどうかを―
調べてみようと思うんだ
No, you shouldn't...
ええ やめときなよ
It's all right.
大丈夫！ 私に作戦があるから
I have a plan.
Nano-chan.
（祐子）なーのちゃん
（東雲(しののめ)なの）あっ はい！
Ah, yes!
（祐子）フフーン
（みお）あっ
Here's a question.
問題です
What is 3260 plus 260 divided by 320?
3,260足す 260割る 320は？
Eh?
（なの）えっ！
（祐子）フフン
Um...
えっとお
Three-thousand two-hundred and sixty plus...
3,260 足す？
うーん 難しかったら ケホッ
If it's too hard for you...
You can use your features.
機能を使っていいけど
ケホッ ケホッ
（みお）ちょい ゆっこ
作戦って それなの？
Wait, Yukko.
That was your plan?
Sorry about that.
すいません
Well, I guess I'll do just that.
じゃあ お言葉に甘えまして
（みお）わあっ
（祐子）釣れた！
I got her!
It's an abacus.
（祐子･みお）そろばんだ
Well, let's see...
えーと ご破算で願いましては…
Start by clearing it...
How basic!
（祐子･みお）本格的だ！
（なの）えっと　１ ２ ３
One, two, three...
（祐子･みお）
ビッ ビッ ビビッビ ビッ ビビ
She's a b-beginner!
ビギナーだあ！
（なの）ええと 3,260足す
Three-thousand two-hundred and sixty plus...
She's not using the abacus!
（祐子･みお）
そろばん 使ってなーい！
（みお）
ちょ… ちょっと ゆっこ？
Hey, Yukko?
あっ 相生さん？
Aioi-san?
（みお）ああ 大丈夫？
Are you okay?
うん 大丈夫
I'm all right.
I get the feeling that was a correct answer in various ways...
いろんな意味で
ご名算な気がしたよ
もう―
Geez.
I told you she's not a robot.
だからロボットじゃないって
言ったでしょ？
Are you okay?
大丈夫ですか？
あっ 飲み物を飲みますか？
Would you like something to drink?
Could it possibly be...?
（祐子）もしかして…
Could it be...?
これ もしかして！
もしかして―
Oil has come!
オイルきた！
It's soup!
（祐子）
すいとんだ！ へコ！
（みお）ゆっこ！
（祐子）ああ…
Yukko!
あっ えっとお…
Um...
あっ 水上(みなかみ)さん
Minakami-san.
Here.
（水上麻衣(まい)）はい
She threw a fastball!
（祐子）直球きた！
（みお）オイル！
Oil!
You can have it.
（麻衣）あげる
Oh, really?
えっ あっ いいんですか？
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
She'll drink it!
（祐子･みお）飲む！
It was a miss!
（祐子）空振った！
（みお）フウ
I want you to have this, too.
（麻衣）これも あげる
A curveball!
（祐子）魔球！
（みお）モンキーレンチ！
A monkey wrench!
Oh, thank you.
あっ すいません　助かります
This'll come in handy.
She'll eat it!
（祐子）食べる？
It was a miss!
（祐子）空振った！
（みお）ハア
Hey, you two should cut this out.
（みお）ちょ… ちょっと
２人とも いいかげんにしなよ
You're troubling Nano-chan.
なのちゃん困ってるでしょ
It's skinship.
スキンシップ
Well, I just wanted to become friends...
いや 友達になりたくて
（みお）もうっ
Geez.
This is a step in the wrong direction.
これじゃ 近づくどころか
遠ざかる一方だよ
Sorry...
（祐子）ご… ごめん
（みお）まったく
Geez...
No, don't worry about it.
いえ  そんな お気になさらずに
（みお）えっ でも…
But...
あっ そうだ
Since you don't need this soup, I'll drink it.
すいとん 要らないなら
飲んじゃいますね
See? Nano-chan says so, too.
（祐子）ほら
なのちゃんも こう言ってるし
Geez. What are you talking about?
（みお）何 言ってんのよ もう
（なの）あれ？
銀歯 取れたかなあ
Did my crown come off?
Put yourself in Nano-chan's shoes and think about it!
（みお）なのちゃんの身になって
考えてみなよ
I want to know.
（中村(なかむら)先生）知りたい
How are they able to make something of such high quality?
なぜ あそこまで高性能なものが
作れるのか
Shinonome Nano, who transferred here the other day...
先日 転校してきた 東雲なの
Her existence...
あの存在感
Yes, that key...
そう あのネジ
No matter how you look at her, she is a robot.
どうみてもロボット
Why hasn't she been shown to the scientific community?
あれほどのロボットを
学会で発表せず―
Why is she attending this school as if it isn't a big deal?
なぜ こんな学校に
のほほんと登校させているのか
I want to research.
調べたい
I want to research her.
彼女を調べたい
And I want to make her mine.
そして―
私のものにしたい
Nichijou 60
Oh, Nakamura-sensei.
中村先生
頼まれた本 持ってきました
I brought the books you asked for.
She's here!
（中村）
来た！ よし 決行するぞ
All right!
Jump into action!
Well, then, I'll excuse myself.
では 失礼します
Shinonome, hold on a second.
（中村）東雲  ちょっと待て
Would you like some coffee?
どうだ？ コーヒーでも
１杯 飲んでいかんか？
Oh, no, I don't want to trouble you.
えっ いやあ
お手数ですので
Don't make excuses like that.
そんな 水くさいことを言うな
I was just making some.
今 いれたところだ
It's a thank you for bringing me the books.
本を頼んだ せめてものお礼だ
飲んでいけ
Just drink some.
Well, then, just one cup.
あっ じゃあ １杯だけ
First, I'll test whether or not sleeping medicine works on her.
（中村）まずは睡眠薬が
効くかどうか試してやる
If that doesn't work, I'll use the "Short Circuit-kun" that I created yesterday on her from behind.
これがダメなら―
昨日 作った 回路ショート君を
背後から くらわせてやる
Here, drink up.
（中村）まあ 飲め
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
フン
飲んじゃった
I drank it!
うっ 耐えろ
I must endure.
I must endure!
耐えろ
（なの）では失礼します
Well, I'll excuse myself now.
（中村）せめて
At least...
Use Short Circuit-kun...
回路ショート君を
Short Circuit-kun...
回路ショート君を…
Oh, that's right.
あっ そうそう
理科の中村 倒れたらしいよ
I heard the science teacher, Nakamura, fainted.
よく倒れるなあ 中村
She sure faints a lot. Nakamura, that is.
（少年１）
ギョー ギョギョギョー ギョギョー
ギョー ギョー ギョー
（なの）ハア
That was pretty close today.
今日は危なかったなあ
But Aioi-san and Minakami-san seem like really good people.
けど 相生さんも水上さんも―
本当は すごく いい人そうだし
Maybe they could become my friends...
ひょっとしたら友達に…
Take this!
（少年２）くらえ！
Rocket punch!
（少年２）ロケットパーンチ！
（少年１）ギヨー！
（少年２）ぽっかーん！ ババババ
（少年１）ギョギョ ギョー
（少年２）
これがロケットパンチの
マキシムパワーだ！
This is the maximum power of a rocket punch!
（少年２）ガーガガガ
（少年１）ギョッ ギョー！
（なの）ハア
Shinonome Institute
Professor, Professor!
（なの）はかせ はかせ！
Oh, Nano, welcome back.
（はかせ）あっ なの  おかえり
あっ なの  おかえり
Oh, Nano, welcome back.
Huh? Why did you say it twice?
なんで２回 言うんですか？
Wait. More importantly,
…って そんなことよりですね
can you hurry up and take this off of me?
早くこれ 取ってくださいよ
Nichijou 61
なんで？
Why?
（なの）なんでって
だって イスには座りにくいし―
Because it's hard for me to sit in a chair.
Everyone looks at me like I'm strange,
みんなには
変な目で見られるし―
and on top of that, I was recorded on video.
その上 ビデオにまで
撮られたりして―
I had to try to cover it all up.
それでもなんとか
ごまかしたんですよ
ええ！ カワイイのに
But it's cute.
But people won't treat me like a
normal girl if I have this key attached.
ネジがついてたら―
みんな普通の女の子扱い
してくれないじゃないですか
You'll definitely get popular.
絶対 人気 出るから
ヤですよ！
No, I don't want to.
I just want to live a normal school life...
私は普通の学校生活を！
（はかせ）テヘッ
（なの）ううっ
（はかせ）わあっ！
（なの）ハア ハア ハア
もう なんで こんな
ウエポンつけるんですか？
Why did you put a weapon like this on me?
I'm glad it didn't come out at school.
学校で取れなくてよかった
Why don't you want people to find out you're a robot?
なのは なんで
ロボだってバレたくないの？
It's obviously because robots aren't cute.
（なの）
そんなのカワイくないからに
決まってるじゃないですか
ロボはカワイイよ！
Robots are cute!
カワイくないですよ！
They are not cute.
They're cute!
カワイイ！
This gun is, too?
このガンもですか？
It's cute!
カワイイ
The toe USB, too?
いつぞやの親指ＵＳＢとか？
カワイイ！
It's cute!
Sweets coming out of my forehead, too?
額から甘食とか？
It's cute!
カワイイの！
Geez!
もう！ はかせのマッド博士！
Professor, you're a mad professor!
It's cute!
I want to be more normal!
私は もっと 普通が いいんです！
（なの）
わあい ちくわだあ アハハハ
Wow, it's a chikuwa!
TL Note: Chikuwa is a tube-shaped fish cake.
Chikuwa sure is delicious.
（はかせ）
ちくわって おいしいよね
（なの）ハア ハア ハア
（なの）ハア ハア
Three, two, one...
（はかせ）３ ２ １
（ハト時計の音）
（なの）わああっ！
（なの）ハア ハア
（ハト時計の音）
Daihuku Fair ①
All right, we have daihuku!
（青年）
はーい 大福だよ！ 安いよ！
They're cheap!
It's daihuku!
大福だよ！
Oh, Nakanajou-san.
あっ 中之条(なかのじょう)さん
お疲れさまでーす！
Good work!
（中之条さん）ふーん！
Daihuku don't talk!
大福が しゃべるな！
I'm sorry... but I...
（青年）
すいません でも俺―
Daihuku Fair ②
なまはんかな気持ちで
これ かぶってないっすから！
I'm not doing this half-heartedly!
I'm putting my life on the lin-
命 懸けてますか…
（中之条さん）ぬわあっ
Don't make me say it so many times!
何べんも言わすな！
Crap, I failed last time.
（中村）
クソッ この前は失敗した
The sleeping medicine scheme was badly thought out.
やはり睡眠薬は
軽率すぎたな
Nakamura-sensei, Short Circuit-kun
After all, she is a robot.
なにせ
やつはロボットだ
She probably won't lose consciousness without a really powerful hit.
強力な１発がなければ
失神すらしてくれないだろう
And that's where this comes in!
そこで これだ！
I wasn't able to test it out before.
このあいだ 試せなかった
対ロボット用 回路ショート君
For use against robots, Short Circuit-kun!
Using this, I can knock her out.
これで やつを気絶させ
今日こそ捕獲してやる
Today, I'll finally capture her.
It's almost time.
そろそろ時間だ
（中之条 剛(つよし)）ぎゃああ！
（中村）逃げろ！
Run away!
Oh, Nakamura-sensei!
（なの）あっ 中村先生
Hey, you can't leave your top button undone!
（桜井(さくらい)先生）ちょ… ちょっと！
一番上のボタン
締めなきゃダメだよ！
（桜井 誠(まこと)）うるさいなあ もう
べつに俺の勝手だろ
Jeez. You're annoying.
I can do it if I want to!
No, you can't!
ダメ！ 私 これでも
生徒指導なんだから
I may not look like it, but I'm actually in charge of student guidance!
（誠）ゲエッ！ まじかよ
よくなれたな
Seriously?
How did you get that position?
How rude!
失礼ね！ ほら ちょっと貸して
Here, let me do this.
（誠）自分でやるって
恥ずかしいな
I'll do it myself.
This is embarrassing.
Um...
（高崎(たかさき)先生）ええっと…
What's going on?
ドユコト？
Nichijou 62
Well, Mako-chan, you can't fix it yourself, can you?
だって マコちゃん
自分で直せないでしょ？
（高崎）ああっ マコちゃん？
You really are annoying.
"Mako-chan"?
Come on!
What are you doing?
（誠）何すんだよ お前は
やめろって！
You
Stop it!
I'll button it for you.
（桜井）いいから
ほら つけてあげるから
Button It
"You"? "Button it"?
（高崎）お前？ つけてあげる？
Don't hang around me at school!
もう！ あんまり学校で からむなよ
H... "Hang around"?!
（高崎）か… からむ？
えーと えーと
えーと どういう関係？
What kind of relationship do they have?
See? It came off.
（桜井）
ほら 取れちゃったでしょ
That's just perfect.
（誠）ああ ちょうどよかったよ
じゃあ 俺 用事があるから
Well, I have stuff to do, so bye.
（桜井）あっ ちょっと待って
Hey! Hold on!
そんな だらしない格好してたら
みんなに笑われちゃうよ
You'll be laughed at if you look sloppy like that.
なんだよ お前だって
家じゃ だらしない格好してるだろ
What's with you?
You're always sloppy at home, aren't you?
At home!?
（高崎）家で？
S-Sloppy-looking!?
だだだ… だらしっ
だらしない格好？
Sloppy-looking, yes!
だらしない格好 よし！
No, that's not right!
違う 違う 違う！
よしとか言って俺はアホか！
Am I an idiot for getting excited like that?
And why is a Chinese dress sloppy!?
なんでチャイナ服が
だらしない格好なんだよ！
It's just a normal sloppy-looking appearance!
普通に だらしない格好だろ
What am I thinking?
何 考えてんだ？ 俺は
教師として恥ずかしいと思わんのか
I should be ashamed as a teacher!
普通に だらしない格好だよ 普通に
A normal sloppy-looking appearance...
Sloppy-looking!
だらしない格好
Good enough!
イナフ！
What's good enough, idiot?!
イナフって おい！ バカ！
Well, I'm leaving now.
いいから  俺 もう行くよ
Hey, what about the button?
ちょっと ボタンは？
Oguri Cap is like this!
ウェ ウェ ウェッヘ！
ワン！
ワン
Idiot!
（高崎）…って バカ！
Well, I'm leaving now.
（誠）いいから  俺 もう行くよ
Hey, what about the button?
（桜井）ちょっと ボタンは？
（高崎）あっ！
I'll go after them!
（高崎）お… 追うぞ
Takasaki-sensei!
（安中(あんなか)）高崎先生！
Nakanojou-kun passed out in the science room!
理科室で 中之条君が
失神しちゃってるんですけど
I need you to come immediately!
（安中）
すぐ来てほしいんですけど
（桜井）ちょっと待って
（高崎）わあっ！
Wait!
Drop it!
（誠）もういいだろ！
All right.
いいか よく聞け！
Listen up.
（安中）はい
Yes?
Nakanojou hasn't passed out!
中之条は 失神していない！
That's right!
そうだ！ 仮眠かもしれん
He might just be taking a nap!
だって 白目
むいちゃってるんですけど
But his eyes have gone completely white!
Draw them in!
書き込め
やってみます
I'll try it!
ちょっと待て！
Wait!
あれは！
W-What is going on there?!
あれは どういうことなんだ？
Watching out for illicit relationships is more important than someone passing out!
失神よりも不純異性交遊を
取り締まることのほうが―
教育者としての なんだ その…
That's an educator's... Um, well, what it means to be an educator!
教育者だ！
That's Sakurai-sensei's younger brother!
あれ 桜井先生の弟さんですけど
行くぞ！
Let's go.
Okay.
はい
All right. Here it goes.
（高崎）よーしきた！
I'll hurry on.
急いで行くぜ！ それが…
That's what being a teacher is about.
教師ってもんだろ
（安中）こっちです！
It's this way!
（はかせ･なの）ピョン ピョン
（はかせ）うう ピョン
（なの）ピョン
（はかせ）ピョン
（はかせ）ポン
（はかせ･なの）ばあ
Love-Like
Taking Home
Next stop: Kokusadame Station, north entrance.
（アナウンス）次は 時定(ときさだめ)駅北口
The bus will stop.
（アナウンス）次 止まります
（男子高校生１）ブハハハッ
（男子高校生１）ハハハハ
Hey, you're not getting off there.
お前 次じゃねえだろ？
I just wanted to press the button.
（男子高校生２）いやあ なんか
押したくなっちゃうんだよね ヘヘ
Didn't you press it earlier?
（男子高校生１）
お前 さっきも押してなかった？
（男子高校生２）
さっきは降りた人いたから
結果的によかったじゃん
Someone got off then, so it was fine in the end, right?
（男子高校生１）なるほど
人助けってやつだな
I see. So it's like helping someone out.
See? Someone got off here.
（男子高校生２）ほらあ
ここも降りる人いたじゃんか
（男子高校生１）お見事！
Well done!
Hey Mum, do we have a tear-off calendar?
お母さん　日めくりカレンダー
なかったっけ？
Isn't there one in the cupboard?
（祐子の母）
押し入れにあるんじゃないの？
Shinonome Institute
Professor! Professor!
（なの）はかせ はかせ！
Oh, Nano. Welcome back.
あっ なの　おかえり
Could you please just remove this key?
もう！ いいかげん
このネジ 外れないんですか？
It causes so many problems for school life!
学校生活に
支障きたしまくりなんですから
For the high jump, all I could do was a belly roll!
今日の体育なんか―
高跳びでベリーロールしか
できなかったんですよ
I got called off-sides in soccer, too.
サッカーしたとき―
これのせいで
戻りオフサイド取られたし
それ 取れるよ
It can be taken off.
（なの）ズコー！
Nichijou 63
もう 取れるなら
早く言ってくださいよ
You should have told me earlier if it could be taken off!
Understood.
分かった
今 取ってあげます
I'll take it off right now.
Every day of youth is important.
青春の１日１日は
貴重なんですからね
でも これでやっと
普通の高校生活が送れますよ
But now, I can finally live as a normal high schooler.
Could you please hurry and take it off?
早速ですが
取ってもらってもいいですか？
Stare
Professor, that's...
はかせ それって
もしかして…
Could it possibly be...
I took it.
TL Note: "Toru" means "to take off" as in to remove, but also "to take" as in a photo.
撮った
（なの）ヘコー！
Oh, no!
ああ もう もう…
Please don't make stupid jokes like that!
写真で撮るなんて
いにしえのギャグやめてくださいよ
ごみん ごみん
Sorry, sorry.
So, can this key be removed?
…で このネジは外れるんですか？
Well...
それは…
う－ん
ぐう
（なの）ボカーン！
I don't want any more stupid jokes!
古き良きギャグは
要らないですから！
So, can you take it off or not?!
取れるんですか？
取れないんですか？
I can.
取れる 取れるよ
はかせは あまたのネジを
取ってきた人だよ
I've taken lots of keys before.
Yours can be easily...
なののネジなんか
簡単に取れます　パシャ
Taken.
（なの）コイン コイン コイン
すぽーん！
Coin! Coin! Coin! Zoom!
キャハハハ
フフッ コイン コインって言った
You went "Coin! Coin! Coin!"
コイン すぽ すすすっ
すぽーんって
Then, you went "Z-Zoom!"
Professor, I have a question.
はかせ！ 質問があります
ハア 息が… 息ができない
My breath...
I can't breathe...
笑いすぎて
I laughed too much.
Professor, I've been having really unnatural reactions all day today.
はかせ  私 今日―
なんか不自然な
こけ方してるんですけど
Have you done anything?
何か その…
してませんか？ 私に
To me?
Actually, yesterday, I added a reaction feature to you.
実は昨日 こけ機能をつけました
（なの）シビビーン
シビビーン シビビーン シビビーン
What kind of messed up feature is that supposed to be?!
ちょ ちょ ちょっ！
何ですか その すちゃらか機能は
なんで そんな機能
つけたんですか！
Why would you add a feature like that?
面白そうだから
Because it seemed funny.
（なの）コケー！
Reaction!
Goal!
ゴール！
（はかせ）チュッ
（なの）オター！
（阪本(さかもと)）ハア
I'm going to die.
（なの）死ぬ このままだと
こけ死んでしまう
If this continues, I'm going to die from these reactions.
See? Isn't it funny?
ねっ 面白いでしょ？
It's not funny at all!
（なの）面白くないです！
Professor, putting the key aside,
はかせ  ネジは
あと回しでいいんで―
could you please remove this feature?
この機能を取ってください
That'll be a hundred yen.
（はかせ）じゃ 百円
（なの）セコー！
（阪本）うわっ ぐわっ くくっ
Word Of The Day
This is my maximum capacity.
I'm Oil.
（オイル）オイルです
スベっているってよく言われます
I've been told that I'm slippery.
いやあ でもオイルだけに
しかたないか…
But I'm oil, so I can't really help it.
的な まとめを
上司に よくされます
I'm told that a lot by my boss.
Who's the boss of Oil?
オイルの上司って誰だよ！
Next episode of Nichijou is episode 16.
次回の「日常」は
第16話
Narration:      Sakakibara Yoshiko
Be prepared.
お楽しみに